Henry Botkin Papers
Henry Botkin Papers
1928-1965
Botkin, Henry Albert, 1896-1983.
0.5 linear ft.
American painter and illustrator. Collection includes correspondence, printed material, photographs, clippings.
2744136
Biographical History
Henry Botkin (1896-1983) was an American abstract, modern and expressionist painter and illustrator; he was known for his figure-views, still lifes, and non-objective paintings. He was active in artistic circles, served as president of four major art organizations (Artists Equity Association, American Abstract Artists, Group 256 Provincetown, and Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors), and in 1955 organized the first exhibition of American abstract art at the Museum of Modern Art in Tokyo, Japan.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Henry Botkin Papers consists of biographical material, correspondence, manuscript material, photographs, published material and subject files.
Biographical material contains a biographical sketch of Botkin from the 1948 Marquis International Who's Who.
Correspondence includes letters to or from Botkin's wife and fellow painter Anna Walinska, along with a few unidentified letters.
Manuscripts contains an assortment of material by and about Botkin, including a book outline, press releases, some pencil sketches, speeches and discussions.
Photographs are of Botkin, his work, and the work of others.
The bulk of Published material is comprised of newspaper clippings by and about Botkin; there are also some reproductions of Botkin's work and some exhibit material. Two books originally with the collection have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
Subject files includes financial material (bills, receipts, etc.), an essay on abstrac art in Japan by Sabro Hasagawa, a few building plans and meeting minutes from several organizations to which Botkin belonged.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical.
Separated Material
Two books (listed in inventory below) have been sent to Rare Books for cataloging.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Botkin, Henry Albert, 1896-1983.; Expressionism (Art); Painting, Abstract.; Painting, America -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Henry Botkin, 1965.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical material, 1948; "International Who's Who" published by the A.N. Marquis Co. (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Mrs. Botkin, 1937-1962; handwritten and typed letters; photocopied letters (Box 1)
  - Anna Walinska, 1928-1965; handwritten and typed letters; photocopied letters (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1919-1939; handwritten letters; photocopied letters (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - About Botkin's work, 1927-1959; critiques and reviews (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical, undated (Box 1)
  - By Botkin, 1944; undated; outline for book; writings on art and artists (Box 1)
  - Gallery press releases by Botkin, 1957-1962; Gallery 256; Karlis Gallery; Museum of Modern Art (Box 1)
  - Gallery press releases mentioning Botkin, 1957-1962; Gallery 256; Karlis Gallery (Box 1)
  - "Henry Botkin" by anonymous, undated (Box 1)
  - Pencil sketches by Botkin, undated (Box 1)
  - Speeches and discussions, 1958; undated; first draft for forum-Museum of Modern Art; copy of Botkin's part in panel discussion for federation meeting; discussion with Mr. Segy and Mrs. Story (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Negatives, undated (Box 1)
  - Of works of others, undated; from Henry Botkin to George Gershwin (Box 1)
  - Of Botkin's work, 1928-1961 (Box 1)
  - Of Henry Botkin, circa 1950; undated (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Book, Art: From Life to Life by A. Walkowitz, Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
  - Exhibitions, 1935-1965; newspaper clippings and promotional material (Box 1)
  - Exhibition catalog, Catalogue des Tableaux Modernes, 1928; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
  - Newspaper clippings about Botkin, 1929-1963; undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings about others, 1929-1956; undated; B.A. Botkin; Gershwin; Curry; Glackens; Lahey; Kern; Zanuck; Edzard; Cezanne (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings by Botkin, 1958; "One-Man Shows at Karlis Gallery" (Box 1)
  - Reproductions of Botkin's work, 1923-1961 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Bills, receipts, checks, invoices, 1957-1960 (Box 1)
  - Building plans, Artist's Equity, 1952; undated (Box 1)
  - Hasegawa, Sabro, "Abstract Art in Japan Today" and vitae, undated; essay and notes (Box 1)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1952-1953; Artist's Equity Association Board of Directors; Building Administration Board (Box 1)